[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
um welcome to the store the stove is a
place for us to coherent dialogue at the
knife's edge
what matters most at this very moment
i'm nick benjamin your host for this
second session with sensemaker and
resident zack stein
last week zack introduced his approach
to metapsychology
and described a framework for exploring
and understanding the psyche
so the structure zack's presentation
will
be followed by a q a while zac's
presenting
please write your questions in the chat
and you can unmute yourself
when i call on you to ask your question
um
given that this is being recorded and
put on youtube just let me know if you
want me to ask your question for you
please say it in the chat and i'll uh
and i'll do so
so without further ado take it away zach
thanks uh super happy to be here again
uh sunny kind of beautiful day in
vermont and
uh feeling honored kind of happy
to just have the space and the privilege
to dive deep into these kinds of issues
with you folks
just kind of like holding the kind of
grace
of the moment so i'm going to do the
slide thing again
and try to get through the rest of my
slides today
because the plan is to leave the last
two sessions
as something like a practicum where we
bring
issues from our lives or from the
culture
and we have a little bit more discussion
and try to apply
the metapsychology so that's my hope so
it's going to be like drinking from the
fire hose again today where i just run
through the slides and kind of just
lay a bunch of things out um i'm going
to try to go through
a little bit of a rehearsal last time
and then move through each of the three
modalities of the psyche so
insolent development transcendence
and try to talk about how they weave
together uh so let me get the screen
sharing going here
all right
so let's do this again just to rehearse
where we were um so you'll remember it
was like
we did a journey through the birth and
history of psychology
after realizing that the issue of psyche
was rebrute to the contemporary
metacrisis kind of went over a little
bit of like my existential angst in
graduate school
when i discovered just what a mess the
field of psychology was as a science
and then my first attempts to use
charles sanders purses
metaphysics to
kind of rescue psychology from itself to
build a metapsychology
that serves as a mediator between
metaphysics and the sciences of
psychology
right so that's the place where we're
playing is in metapsychology
which isn't the science of psychology
because it's critiquing it and norming
it
but nor is it metaphysics it's like the
bridge between
and so that meta psychology move that i
just made happens in other fields too
and if you look at interdisciplinary uh
research which is to say the people who
reflect on the practices of
interdisciplinarity
you'll find that yeah if you reach the
high end of like biology
you get into something like metabiology
and if you reach the high end of
sociology you get into
meta-sociology and many of those meta
disciplines which bridge philosophy and
metaphysics and the discipline itself
many of them have commonalities and
that's where you get this kind of
move towards consilience in the space of
uh
knowledge construction so this is an
attempt to build a metapsychology
off of purse but of course
especially with landry and so by the
time
two or three years ago i returned to
metapsychology
as a focus i had a better
grasp of how that tripartite metaphysics
metapsychology psychology thing could
work
so this is what i'm presenting so
transcendence and soulmate development
is my characterization of these deeper
uh kind of meta theoretical and
metaphysical distinctions
that are that are around so you'll
recall
i broke these down into the different
triads within them language cognition
capacity as a set
involved with development which captures
a whole range of psychological
disciplines including developmental
psychology cognitive science
etc uh insolent image imagination
personality which captures usually
what's called depth psychology
but particularly encapsulating more of
the
union and even artistic and aesthetic
dimensions
of that element of psyche
and then transcendence symbol attention
consciousness
here you also find uh formal
psychological sciences especially
affective neuroscience uh the study of
meditation
altered states things of that nature but
you find also where religion and
psychology
come together um especially in ritual
and
symbol and uh transcendent consciousness
and awareness
so that's the set and the idea is that
this encapsulates
everything that kind of wants to call
itself the
science of psychology kind of organizes
it and then allows us to see
that the psyche is actually very
polysemic
which means it has multiple meanings and
lends itself to analysis from all three
angles at all times
which means like if any paid give me any
behavior
and i can look at it from developmental
perspective an installment perspective
or a transcendence perspective
and if you are behaving in the world
especially if you're behaving well
which is to say that it is a net
generative to your own
future growth and learning and positive
to the environment
uh all three of these are happening in
your behavior in a certain way which is
it's kind of like saying like your whole
brain your
whole brain is actually involved in
every behavior
so the whole psyche is actually involved
in every behavior
so this is where it gets kind of
interesting because when you look across
these three
you will find that there are this is
where the metaphysics comes in
deeper patterns that show up across all
three
and this is an example now stages and
stations and phases are distinct
because they don't work in exactly the
same way but they're also similar
because they involve this kind of like
rolling over and moving into
uh and having certain spaces that
are containment and stability
so in the state place of stages where
you're residing at a stage
and then some kind of shift to another
way of operating
and that happens in stations as well and
it happens in phases
so you got to see how these are like
similar the underlying thing
metaphysically is
uh what bhaskar called basically
dialectic
what landry would call the axiom2
rotation
but it's a common underlying pattern of
all of them
but it's very important to see how
they're different uh so as i move
through each of these later
i'll talk more about what the
differences between stages and stations
and phases is
here i'm just saying that there's
something that all three of these do
and it's that they transform they
transform through a rhythmic
identifiable pattern
they also interrelate um this is another
example of an axiom two
rotation um from landry's imminent
metaphysics
uh so as i described last time this is
like an ooda loop
this is also like the circular reaction
which was this
kind of basic early conception in
psychology that dewey and
james and others toyed with the basic
idea is that installment the domain of
personality you get a motivation
you get an image of this situation
you're in and yourself
and then that basically propels
development because the image is always
a problematic the image always has
behavior
required action required so you need to
have capacity
actualize so you move into development
objectify the world build the skill
necessary and then part of you somehow
acts choice right
transcendence is not otherworldly
transcendence is actually
like where the body is it's about you
as an uncaused cause in the causal chain
it's about the power of choice
but also putting insolent and
development
in view both of them which means it has
a dimension of
uh witness or distance
in any case and then once you've chosen
enacted then the personality is back and
what's the image is the image changed
have i became who i thought i would be
from the action
has it worked am i have i resolved the
tragedy
or have i fixed the problem um
and then it repeats right if it's
working well
then this thing really becomes auto
catalytic kind of
psychic evolution structure
so as i mentioned last time this is
review still
uh all four quadrants are involved in
each
which means that moving through
developmental stages is an all-quadrant
fair
moving through stations of insolent is
an all-quadrant affair
moving through phases of consciousness
and emotion
is also in all quadrant affair so it's
not like
they do kind of correspond with the
quadrants
but it's not like one of them means this
is this quadrant and
in fact they're all in all quadrant
affair which is key and they all
as i mentioned have these underlying
dynamics which are deeper and have to do
with
nonlinearity phase shift chaos and
complexity dynamics which means that
there's uh there's nothing in this that
is
mechanistic um and a lot of this
is organismic
in the white hedian sense and i'm going
to get in more into that when i get into
development in particular
so as i said they have commonalities as
i mentioned
just now the quadrants the dynamics the
underlying metaphysical triples
but there's also distinct content form
and process
and so that's where we get into like
cognition uses
language and semiotics of symbol
representation
and objective frames etcetera you know
insolent uses image
right transcendence has awareness and
symbol
so you'll see there's differences too um
and here's where it gets kind of
interesting is that they co-arise
they mutually enmesh and they
reciprocally enable and the reciprocally
enabling is interesting so
one important dynamic that i'll get into
is that
so you're moving around from installment
through development to
transcendence when you reach certain
stages of development and it kicks
through
and comes back to installment you can
actually open
the door to stations of insolent
through the actualizations of stages of
development
right so uh
an example of that would be that
if you are pursuing the vocation of a
healer like a doctor
or an herbalist or something of that
nature um
and you acquire a certain capacity of
doing that
in development you have the languages of
it the cognition involved in making
considered judgments and diagnostics and
you become
capacity in that way you've now opened
the door to go through the kind of
installment process
that is possible when you take on the
responsibility of being a doctor healer
right you can't go through that's those
stations
of like the wounded healer and the
moving into the like
light of god type healing stuff like
none of that starts to happen to you
unless you've built the developmental
capacity to step into the space of
actually being
that person same with certain forms of
certain forms of teaching
certain forms of science and scholarship
so the notion that moving through
certain levels getting certain
capacities can then open the door to
certain stations
is interesting uh similarly stations
that are more let's say primordial to
the deeper image of yourself
those will set the rudder for certain
types of developmental things to come
online
right
some people at a very early age it's
clear that music
music is like in their soul right and
then that prints
them towards a certain kind of stage
development in
kinesthetic musical aesthetic dimensions
so you can see this intermeshing
intertwining and i could we have similar
stories about
transcendence where certain states of
consciousness become readily available
make it easier to move through
certain stages right so you have to get
how all of this
moves together and there's a lot of
complexity which is like implicit in the
model which would take a long time for
me to actually speak to
but there's a whole kind of like
grid-like structure there
so and then as we talk about the deeper
dimensions especially when we talk about
him at the level of language of
insolent transcendent development
to be careful i will always make
mistakes in doing this but we have to be
careful
uh these things aren't within the psyche
they're not like parts of the psyche
like a functionalist
model and they're also not structures
technically
i like to think about them as basically
primordial
categories in terms of which the psyche
understands itself
so these are part of the psyches
relationship with itself
and therefore its relationship with
other
other quote unquote psyches which is to
say you and me
i and thou so it's something that's
emerged from that dimension of our
experience
all right so let's move through
let's move through each of the three
um and as i move through i'm going to be
making meta commentary of how they
interact interrelate or at least
i'm intending to do that so hopefully
i'll be good to my own attention
all right so there's uh when we move
into the domain of installment i like to
start
with installment but you can start with
any of them
the reason i start with in solomon is
because it's uh
the most imminent it's the one that is
you could argue kind of like begins
when the process has a beginning it
begins from
who you are right begins from the root
metaphors or archetypes in terms of
which you understand yourself
and the world uh
so james hillman is kind of the key
person here and the term insolent is
never fed so much helmet i couldn't find
that actual
term and uses the word soul making um
researchers in the space bedroom is
definitely the leader um
you know ran the jung institute for a
while uh
met jung on his death bed um uh
deeply transformed the field of depth
psychology both in terms of
criticizing the practice of psychiatry
and
psychology as a like a medical
biomedical discipline
and also changing the stream of union
depth psychology uh
into something that became as flexible
kind of flexible deeply powerful um
set of frames so i'm a big fan of helmet
work a lot of what i'm saying here is
just coming from
from hill and i'll try to mention some
books along the way
so image imagination personality and
stations right so this is this is what
that play
in insolent and
so the key dimension of
uh let's say
growth or deepening
that takes place here uh is
characterized by jung basically in terms
of
emotional maturity or individualization
uh it's also posited as one of the
dimensions of
maslow's developmental uh model
so you have to get that many
much psychology that's gone on uh has
put a couple of these in the triple
together
so like maslow's development
developmental model and some
ego psychology models like lavender
actually blend in solvent and
development together which isn't a
problem i'm trying to differentiate them
a little bit for
clarity but ego development and you know
maslow's model and some other ones blend
them together but there's elements of
maslow's model
that gets that are station-like and that
work with the image of
self and
so to even begin to move through this we
need to clarify what do we mean by an
image
and what do we mean by a station so i'm
going to set down some terminology and
then that'll
free the conversation up so you can see
what i'm talking about
so that's a picture of a symbol
symbols are extremely powerful and
they're extremely universal
and they are attached basically to the
this modality of the transcendent
focusing of awareness and there's a
impersonal element where i actually
kind of de-identify with the local ego
and identify with the symbol
beyond so that's kind of an important
difference i'm going to move between
them
so that's a painting of an image
right jotto uh one of the very kind of
first
uh people to use what we would call
modern perspective
um so you can see that within the image
so let's say i have a dream and i have a
dream that's basically a
reconstruction of the crucifixion it
looks a little bit like this
within the dream i can extract a symbol
and this is a lot of what happens in
dream analysis and psychology you have a
dream there's a cross
in it and i say ah the universal symbol
see your dream points you beyond
yourself
to something universal right
but what you're neglecting are the
details of the image
and actually the uniqueness of the image
because if i have a dream about the
crucifixion
it's likely that either i'm on the cross
or i'm somewhere in here as a character
right so like look at
the guy on the right who's with the
romans presumably who has one of the
halos over his head
like that would be an interesting dude
to be in this image if i knew more about
christian uh someone probably knows who
that is here on the calls to put it in
the chat but i'm sure that's
a identifiable guy and then the angels
like look at the angels who are
tormented the one on the right below
jesus's armpit exposes his chest
in in turmoil so like the richness and
the detail of the image is where the
image is
at like that's the point of the image so
it can be
relieving if you're overwhelmed by
the complexity of your own image of self
it can be relieving to find the
universal symbol in it which identifies
you with the transpersonal
which gets you out of the complexity of
the omniscient
trying to understand developmentally
what's going on in the image and the
torture and the tragedy of the image
pull out the cross and boom you've moved
your attention has switched
phase shift and emotion and you see the
transcendent right so that's
a lot of what's useful to do in dream
work but for helmand
and i would say from the perspective of
insolent
the idea is to actually linger and
deepen within the power
and unicity uniqueness of the image
so here's another image right this one's
the return of persephone
so that's hermes who who's rescuing
persephone
from hades returning to demeter
uh her mother um incredibly powerful
image
but you have to get that an image is
always has a context
a setting and a mood so not all pictures
are images
images are mythogens or
i can't i don't know how to say that but
it means basically means like fragment
of a myth
and uh so this one's powerful right
i mean the gesture of openness like
demeter looking like a little bit like
christ there on the cross
uh but then the proneness of
persephone's head
um the composure of hermes uh
the plant down in the lower left
likely to be aconite which is uh
grew from the saliva of cyborus the
three-headed dog
at the door of hades is actually an
incredibly poison
no it's my wife mag and she identified
that
in this image so there's richness to an
image a uniqueness to the image
which you don't want to so what you
could do here is you could say ah the
mother
the mother right you could extract the
mother archetype
into the realm of symbol from the
richness and unicity
of that right or you could do it with
any other figures in it
right and so i'm not saying don't do
that
but i'm saying that's not the only thing
to do with image you can
move to the impersonal universal
symbol or you can stay and clarify the
uniqueness and clarify the uniqueness of
the image itself
um so this from one of my favorite
movies
uh the fountain by darren arnovski
uh so this is another potent image like
a fragment of a myth
and you don't even need to know the
whole story here but there's enough
complexity within the moving parts here
that you can describe it in this crazily
textured imaged way so right it's like
i stand at the edge of my world a woman
walks to me from a tree
right the trees died space all around
something like that it sounds like
you're rehearsing a dream
and then for hillman what you do is you
would move through the different
components of the image
to try to clarify the archetypal nature
of the image
we'll return to that but you can see
what i'm getting at is that
these are paintings and screenshots from
uh but you could put your dream from
last night
right there i can that's the insight
is that the image is the like
it's what we traffic in when we traffic
in
insolent or personality
so you could also put the spontaneous
constructions
of your imagination during the last time
you cried lost your temper or could not
sleep
so dream is the classic
kind of place where we go to look for
the images that are emerging from
us but so our domains
uh any domain that lends itself to quote
unquote constructive imagination
so this can take place in meditation
practice through
uh intentional exercise
but the psyche generates image like i
said it traffics an image at least a
third of its activity
maybe more is image
metabolization uh and production
so a lot of what you're doing in
kind of like psychotherapy quote-unquote
uh
and other practices which are insolent
oriented is finding ways to
catch the image all right and
work with it and so that's why when i've
spoken about like
crying as a practice of insult
that's what you're actually trying to do
it's like a practice of constructive
imagination
in many ways you're trying to see what
what is the unbearable image
right that's actually haunting you
subconsciously and eating up all of this
emotional
energy to keep out of consciousness
right and identifying that
seeing what it actually is working with
unicity of the image because it's
something to do with your uniqueness
in relationship to others in the world
working through the unicity of the image
then can actually free
that energy um and so then you go deeper
now you've gone deeper
because you've just confronted something
you're actually terrified of
you've gone deeper into the unique story
with the installment
so a couple things here because we're
talking about images so you're getting a
sense of what i mean by
image and the kind of work that we do at
the psychological level with
image right you could argue that
people who are more deeply and sold
let's put it that way who've moved
through more stations
right and i'm about to speak about
stations the stations have to do with
those kinds of transformations and
resolutions
within the arctic imagery of self
and so eventually that becomes conscious
as i've been describing could become a
practice you become aware of the
products of your imagination
and aware of the metabolism you have of
images with
the world which include memory
moments captured in life that stick
right also the works of fiction and your
own
dreams that becomes aware of itself
and so deeply mature kind of been sold
people typically have rich storehouses
of imagery and often end up speaking in
uh richly imagistic metaphorical
language um so there's more about
that but when you're talking about
images in particular you talk about
archetypal images um there's a couple
things we we don't want to get
kind of uh stuck on so the whole like
water archetypes discussion is an
interesting discussion
but we're talking about arc typical
images as opposed to talking about
archetypes we don't need to essentialize
the archetype as often happens with the
practice of removing the symbol
from the image so when you say that
in images archetypal it's different than
saying that there are archetypes in the
image
or that there are archetypes up in some
platonic realm which like manifest
in this image you don't have to say that
to say that the images are typical to
say the image is arctiple is basically
to say that it's
very richly textured with certain
potentially universal connotations
and so like in the demeter one right
there was a mother archetype
there was a daughter archetype right
there was a light darkness heaven hell
archetype right there was also like the
hermet
healing and kind of between world
communication
right all those are typical dimensions
of the image which one's primary i don't
know depends who had the dream
uh so i'd like to speak about archetype
archetypal imagery without getting into
metaphysical debates about archetype um
although those are interesting
this is not the lecture for them and i'm
taking more hillman's
perspective here which is to skew that
metaphysical conversation
and actually focus on our typical
imagery
which means that even if
the archetypal image you're looking at
isn't technically connected to kind of
any of the pantheons of archetypes
right uh you can still have archetypal
imagery
in everyday life which is seemingly
non-divine
or transcendent um and then so the idea
there is that
again as i mentioned the station's like
a pre-tragic tragic
post-tragic um is
uh well it's it's almost perfectly
represented in the
myth of persephone right pre-tragic
persephone picking flowers
right kidnapped into the underworld
stuck completely in tragedy but then
comes back from the underworld but has
to go back there every once in a while
right is in a post-tragic situation
pre-tragic
tragic post-tragic uh and so that's a
transformation
of the basic imagery of the myth and you
could grab
images from each of those stations
right and so when you're looking at your
insolent process that's about
not am i becoming more developed and
complex as a thinker
and not am i deepening awareness of
symbol
control of attention phase change like
meditation kind of
that kind of stuff uh work stasis and
uh you know altered states of
consciousness it's not that
it's about that is the basic root
metaphor or typical image of
self-changing
in the way that they change in mythic
structure
for example so that's the notion of the
station
uh where in development what's being
moved between
stages if you will is cognition language
and capacity
in insolent what goes through this the
movement of stations right is image and
imagination
like and when you think of the
imagination not just that something
happens with your eyes closed
but again a third of the entirety of my
experience right now is the imaginal
which is technically true like you know
i can't see the room behind me well i
can in the video but usually one doesn't
see the room behind me i can't see my
kitchen but it's there
right much of the world picture that i'm
holding now is actually projected
by the psyche as imagination
so again each of these could be a
lecture in itself
and the history of the idea of the
notion of imagination from the medievals
and
through kant and then to people like
jung
and hillman it's a rich conversation but
it's important to get that
when the root archetype in the image of
self changes my imagination itself
changes
so that's what it's like to feel
different in the world because you're
projecting a different
imaginal field onto the world holding a
different image of self in relation to
others
so it's a deep change when you go from
pretty tragic to tragic
right a lot of people are that's
happening to a lot that's happening like
most of the
western world right now even though
we've seen tragedy before
it's been long enough that we forgot and
there's all of these pre-tragic
socialization contexts
uh so to move into the tragic it's
intense
it's a whole shift in underlying
archetypal structure
and then a change of
what of itself
but moving on to post-tragic
so uh so basically the way this cash is
out
in personality uh is that
as i was describing this this
transformation of these imaginable
schemas
of interpersonal interaction so it's
literally the image
of the self in relationship and that
relationships to other people
and to the to the to the physical world
so
who am i what am i the way you answer
that's not with
language and cognition the way you
answer that's with something like an
image
of the self it's pretty rude and
uh so there's a lot more to say there
but i'm gonna move on to development
so installment moves through stations
and as i said
certain stations can't even be moved
through until there's requisite levels
of development
you may recall certain stage
acquisitions open
doors to stations and vice versa
and then all of that trapped into what
you can do
with your awareness and
so i'm going to speak to development
here uh in some detail
so there's piaget's bald head i don't
know if you can see it but this is
psja's office
um and the reason i use this picture is
because
development is messy the
uh stereotypical picture you get of
development
um uh from piaget and textbooks
um through like kohlberg
uh straw man keegan um
other folks it's just that there's this
ladder right that there's just these
stages there's like seven stages and we
give them colors
and we fetishize the stages and we talk
more about the stages
than about let's say how you move
between them
which is weird because that's actually
hugely important
and we use the stages more like
stereotypes to categorize
cultural groups or diagnostics to
denigrate individuals and we don't think
about what does development actually
look like
and when you actually look at the domain
of development
and i'm not even talking about
installment i'm not talking about any
personality emotional dynamics at all
i'm talking about skill
acquisition language development
capacity development across various
domains
it is massively complex it's a complex
dynamical system which psja knew
most of psja was not translated in
english and
in the 80s it was very popular to build
your career on basically
burning uh piaget effigy um
in fact he was one of the most profound
epistemologists of his generation maybe
any generation
and he was a complex dynamical systems
thinker
and so the view i'm going to show you of
development here
[Music]
is different from what you'll get in a
lot of models
and it's the only one that i think that
can actually fit with this broader
picture because as you saw in solomon
was about
unicity right and solomon was actually
about not trying to find this universal
thing in the image but actually trying
to linger in the complexity and unicity
of the image
and similarly development is actually
not about
trying to put yourself at some abstract
universal level
it's about understanding the unicity of
your own developmental
patterns and trajectories and skill sets
and things of that nature
so another deeper metaphysical dimension
behind all three is uniqueness
so language cognition capacity these in
a sense
are deceptively
uh the image imagination personality was
like they were already ambiguous so you
were kind of like on alert
that you need to pay attention to
definitions these ones we think we know
language cognition and capacity are
but they're actually quite complicated
terms again
this could be a lecture on itself just
about development
stages again deceptively simple term
um stages levels
tiers uh orders there's a lot of ways
that
the developmental kind of like
thresholds are described in the
literature i'm going to use stages and
levels mostly interchangeably here
um but here's the actual place to start
so this is baldwin from psychological
review in 1904
uh it's a essay called the genetic
progression of
psychic objects uh and so i don't know
if you guys know integral psychology but
in the back of integral psychology
there's this
set of tables where ken wilber lays out
like dozens of different models across
a common developmental space he calls
altitude
so this is baldwin doing that in 1904
where he basically says listen okay we
know development's universal across
all psychological functions so i'm going
to spec out
along a common developmental kind of
axis
what the different genetic progressions
would be
through the different areas of
the the mind so he looks at the way
logic progresses moving from the second
from the left pre-logical quasiological
logical extraological hyperlogical that
sounds pretty dope what the hell does
that mean right
but this looks a lot like what
developmental theorists do
uh today and then it goes all the way
through modes of individuation
reality attention modes of control
there's a whole thing here baldwin's an
amazing theorist the idea
that he had here was that okay when the
mind develops
piaget would say the same thing you know
a few decades later
when the mind develops it it doesn't
actually go through stages all of one
whole all right so this is that simple
ladder view
that you begin your whole
let's say everything's defined by being
pre-logical
and then everything all of a sudden
moves up across all this defined by
being quasi-logical
uh that's not the case not what baldwin
said then uh never really what psja
said um but it is what you hear from
some developmentalists now
uh the actual idea is that you could be
farther along on some of these lines
than others
and that there's a non-synchronous
right which is to say not all
synchronically moving up at the same
time across temporally
there's developmental differences so
you're looking at a kind of like a
distributed set of skills
that develop asynchronously into this
kind of like dynamic developmental
profile
of skills so this is baldwin's view it's
very important
so and it ended up that the research
ended up kind of playing out that way
that these different domains of
development emerged
so the cognitive and the moral that
there's a difference between building
skill
in operating with the world like
physical objects and
causal systems and there's a and that
and then building
skill and language and operating
in the social domain that those are
distinct
and that they develop asynchronously but
in relation
that was early insight so this is
baldwin and piaget
both making that split and i've kind of
like summarized some models across a few
books
but this is kind of what it looks like
i'll make these slides available on my
website
once the all the lectures are are given
um
so a nom all the way on the right a nami
heteronomy socionami
autonomy these is the way i characterize
the piagetian moral stages
autonomy being what we would call
post-conventional
socio-nami being basically what we would
call conventional
and uh well no those middle to
heteronomy and sociometry being
conventional anomaly being
pre-conventional so and then
there's more work done kolberg focused
on the moral line
in depth armin focused on a line
adjacent to the moral line which is this
line of reasoning about the nature of
the good
as opposed to the just fowler with faith
reasoning his models become
quite famous keegan with self uh
so similar idea that what you have is
like
a whole bunch of different ways of
slicing this developmental pie
because you actually have a massively
distributed set of differentially
developing skill sets
so like almost anything you can speak to
or operate on
can become an independent developing
skill
this is from fisher's skill theory and
then skills weave together into skill
domains
where there are prerequisites that
certain skills need and you use old
skills to build new
skills and things of that nature
so when i
a temporary set of people who focus on
the underlying cognitive structures
which end up being
probably best encapsulated in uh
dawson's electrical assessment system
and commons's model of hierarchical
complexity and so the model of
hierarchical complexity
hierarchical complexity it's a little
bit difficult to say is uh
you know featured pretty prominently in
in metamodernism
uh hanzi francox books and others uh
you know i worked with theo dawson uh
for
many years atletico operationalizing
that in
assessments of um
developmental assessments standardized
developmental assessments
so that that's like when you think about
like the peak of like the science of the
study of developmental stages it's it's
around that consolidation of a common
underlying
metric of hierarchical complexity which
is actually
underlying each of the skill domains
and so it tells you very little it tells
you how
much abstraction and complexity is
embodied in a particular task
uh but it doesn't tell you if the task
has been accomplished well or not
it doesn't tell you if the person
wielding those skills
is moral or anything of that nature but
the distillation of the model of
hierarchical complexity basically marks
the kind of like
watershed moment in the study of
development
i think comparable to hillman's
isolation of the archetypal image as the
root
of insolent station navigation
so and the model of power cool
complexity can be interestedly
represented like this this is
something that kurt fisher probably drew
on the back of a napkin in 1980
and it was one of his kind of most
famous papers kurt was my advisor
recently passed away and
but this is an interesting distillation
and this is again
similar to stations and similar to
phases but different that there's this
change like a change of state like a
qualitative jump
where the output of that lower level
system the cube
the cube becomes the basic element of a
next
system which produces an even much
higher order output
um and so
this is like a model and a
simplification
of the underlying structural properties
of
cognitive development in a whole bunch
of domains
and i'm staying extremely abstract uh
but you can find this discussed about in
more depth
uh on the lactica website there's a
bunch of learnings
um specifically about how to speak
through this
in specific domains i'm not going to do
that i'm staying at a very high level
and then as i described it you know so
that's the way the thing
moves it moves through that deepening of
abstraction and complexity
but it also doesn't move up a ladder of
that it moves out across a dynamic
developmental web
right where the
skill development is very domain
specific and very context
specific so
you can develop social skills quote
unquote in the context of online video
games
right but that's a very specific skill
stack like a very narrow area of this
web
in the broader social skills domain
is text intermediated
like competitive game skill building
with males or something like that right
so like and then the idea that okay
those skills now transfer to the rest of
your social skills is complete nonsense
unless you've found a way to
get them to do explicitly thematized
transfer across domain
right otherwise they're just different
similarly in school if you
teach about critical thinking let's say
in sociology class
right it's very easy for kids to leave
and they build them thinking about oh
social issues are amenable to critical
thinking
and they apply critical thinking skills
uh and they built a skill set of like
doing that bring them to science class
and they may or may not apply that skill
set to
critically thinking about the sciences
right so you can get people who do
social critique all day
who'll just believe medicine
there's like i totally buy medicine like
give me a vaccine
proven by science to work
then they're like boo and they social
justice capitalism and they critique the
hell out of it
because they're good at criticism
systems but they're not deepening the
critique into the whole
into all realms where they could apply
their critical factors right
so that notion of like domain specific
skill acquisition
and skill development up the model of
hierarchical complexity
and then moving out across webs and then
the more attention you give to certain
elements of the web the more that part
of the web grows and
bless this part of the web gross right
so there's actually an
evolutionary competitive tension between
skills within your own development
right and this is a big tension that
emerges especially
depending on the image of yourself in
the domain of installment
when you move into development start
thinking about what do i want to develop
you realize that skills compete skills
compete for time and attention
and your analytical faculties and
critical faculties as i described it
are not easily generalizable if you're
taught to
just focus them on some things so
similarly your ability to exercise those
critical thinking skills that you
learned in
sociology class uh is going to fluctuate
on context so this is the notion of
functional optimal level
when you're in class and your teacher's
there and the book's on the desk and
your supportive
classmates are also engaging in critique
you could operate at sometimes two
levels of hierarchical complexity
beyond where you normally perform now
you go home and you're sitting around
the dinner
table and you're with your parents and
maybe a friend
and you're trying to rehearse basically
those same points you just rehearsed in
class like
four hours ago or something uh and you
try to do that then
and you get some disagreement and then
you you can degrade you can drop down to
what's
sometimes just
uh and operate two complexity levels
below where you're operating in class
all right and you may not or may not be
aware depending upon your transcendence
ability and the emotional state you're
in
and the intensity of the charge of the
image of self of being the person who
talks uh critically or whatever uh so
this is another important point
right it's not a ladder it's a web
and it's not you're at a level it's that
you're in
a range which fluctuates a lot
depending on context and where you are
in the web
and it's all dynamical and this is some
of the most innovative word
work that kurt fisher ever did where he
took mathematical models that he
actually did what the
dynamical systems scientists did
at the kind of stanford institute for
the advanced
study of behavior or something like that
him and robbie case
and paul van giert
and so they put in the parameters of
theoretical models into dynamic system
dynamic systems modeling uh software
and they started to show that okay if
you do think of skills in this way in
terms of hierarchical complexity
self-regulation and differentiated
growers which is different skills
competing for time and attention
you can actually make a system that
moves through a series of wave-like
stages
so this was like a something like
theoretical experimental
psychology where the math itself shows
you the coherence of the basic
underlying theoretical frame it's
another
conversation but these are the two most
interesting models that kurt
produced one just basically shows that
on the left you do get these wave-like
stages of growth over time even when you
have competing
systems that they can cooperate
the one on the right this is called the
psja effect if you take one of the
growers
right one of the skill sets and you
kind of focus on that one to the
detriments of others
early so this would be like taking the
math one out and just drilling the kid
on math
or like tiger woods you take the golf
one out and you just drill on golf
right you end up disregulating the the
whole
system and then the final output is
a spread much more differentiated
developmental profile
which means you're like all spread out
across
different levels different skills are at
different levels which is hard for the
self system
to hold together and so this is like
part of what you get when you start
thinking about one dimensional
man and the distortions of personality
in modern educational systems it's this
kind of dysregulation of coherence skill
integration and development through kind
of like abnormally
trying to boost certain skill domains on
certain
timelines so so that's interesting when
you start thinking dynamical system wise
and you start thinking about multiple
growers
as opposed to
then start thinking about oh wow yeah
interventions and cognitive dimensions
of growth
have ramifications throughout the whole
cognitivism
and the notion of like uh what
the power of integrative uh curricula in
particular become
extremely noted uh again there's i'm
i feel like i'm moving so fast there's
like so much more to say
so i think this is the last one no
there's one more uh so now we're gonna
get micro development
so this is again you're drinking from
the fire hose here and there's a lot of
resources on this
uh so we just saw that like there's
dynamic patterns of growth
and there's interrelation between
growers uh
and now we're seeing that if you look at
this so this is an exchange
of two people they're speaking uh about
a little robotic toy that they're trying
to fix
that's on the table in front of them
this is an experimental situation that
uh kurt and his colleagues set up
actually known as nina grinneau who's at
the sub
and basically over a matter of like an
hour
their conversations move at least three
different levels
of development within that hour so
there's a common misconception like okay
you're at
post conventional you're like quote
unquote second tier or you're yellow or
whatever right that means that you're
always yellow
in all contexts always operating at a
certain very high level of development
but that's just completely incorrect
uh development and what's required of
you is
context specific and there's
overwhelming evidence as this simple
experiment shows that
when you're talking with someone else
about an actual problem in the world
you're forced to move up and down the
developmental register like they had to
build
the ones down in the one that's actions
that's literally picking it up and
looking at it and saying something
concrete about it
and then they start to extract up out
into representations and abstractions
about the object
so when you look at micro development
you're actually seeing these patterns of
moving up and down the developmental
register
very consistently and it would be a
pathology in this case
to only speak about this thing in the
abstract because you actually have to
pick it up
and name things and use indexical
pointing procedures
in the actions and representations
levels to even understand
what it is so yeah again lots of kind of
misconceptions about what it means to be
at certain stages
here's another micro developmental
experiment
this is a therapeutic dyad so this is a
therapist and a patient
speaking over 118
exchanges within a single therapeutic
session and this is tracking both
abstraction
of what's discussed the number of themes
discussed and the emotional salience
and what you're seeing is that in a
psychotherapy therapeutic diet
there's tremendous variability in the
abstraction and complexity of the
language used and the emotional dynamics
so the idea that like oh okay if you're
a coach or a therapist
and you're getting self-authored people
who took a keegan test and they
determined that they were self-authored
and therefore you're going to treat them
in therapy like self-authored people
right maybe maybe not depending how
emotionally triggered they are what
you're talking about and what the dream
was last night
you could end up being way down and
speaking with them at representational
levels getting rich descriptions of
their parents house
or dinner table right so you have to
think in a very complex way when you're
thinking developmentally
very differently actually than than most
of the standard kind of like
here's a ladder of development uh and
your whole person moves through
stages which can be given labels like
colors and things
all right so that's development is done
how's the time do we know what time it
is
yeah we're two coming up on the hour
i have uh 32 minutes left 13 minutes
left
all right i think i'm actually gonna
hold this one and do it at the next
one and take questions on what i just
spoke to because i think if we keep
moving forward
and this can like be certain basic
confusions with what was previously
spoken
then that i don't want to do that so i'm
going to hold this this one will only
take about
maybe 15 minutes or something at the
beginning of the next one and then we
can move into the
practicum it will also give me an
opportunity to put a couple slides
together about
what i want to do in the practicum that
i can show you right before we
begin it uh which will be useful um
cool so let's switch out of this and
into
kind of questions and exchange
fantastic so scott had a question
scott would you like to ask your
question
oh i can't hear you scott
still nothing maybe write it into the
chat box scott
well i can ask i can ask god's question
for him
okay so his first question
pierced his categories are connected to
stages or phases
firstness is exemplified by icons
secondness by indices or contrast
thirdness is symbol bodies of knowledge
libraries
how are these related to your categories
yeah i know the well there's two things
there one is that
there's the persian triple being related
to
stations and stages and then there's the
persian triple red as a semiotic
and how that relates to the three or to
psychology in general
and so it's true that you can lay out
one two three horizontally
as i did transcendence and soma
development but if you look within let's
say development
and that figure that i showed you that
kurt made with the dot
and then the line the barbell and then
the square
and then the cube you can interpret that
also along
the triple right firstness literally the
one dot
secondness the two dots thirdness
being the system and then the new
firstness is also the next role
of the third right so then that's
actually a saying from
alchemy uh first followed by the second
which is followed by the third which is
about followed by the fourth which is
another one
anyway it's a weird mystical saying but
the idea being that
the triple rolls over and it come
becomes the new firstness
um so you can see the person in
categories development
moving that way and then you know
haven't run
the kind of like persian
symbol index icon
with these three i'm wondering if it's
worth trying to think about
doing it right now i mean he had a very
different terminology right so the
symbol for him would be with
language i think the icon
might be image and
the
index might be uh
what we're calling a symbol in my
language so i'd have to work that out
this probably isn't the place to do that
but i think that what i just did might
be correct
but now i can't remember yeah we can't
hear you scott
i have a feeling you're asking very
difficult questions so i feel like it's
probably good
for me that your pointed criticism can't
come through
all right sorry about that scott so
we'll move on to another question
uh sam c you had a question me on you
go ahead
hi zach hey man
i wanted to ask you about the role of
emotions in your framework
you talked last time about emotion
regulation
in transcendence to
you know like descent this this
identified yourself and put your
attention
into what you got to do i understand
that
but i see also emotions
as as a guide for motivation
in deliberate practices in
in the developmental realm
and also as a guide for the intuition
that guides you into the installment
process so how
how do you see emotions moving into your
framework
how do you work with them and how do you
alchemically purify them so they are the
guide
and you just don't this disidentify with
them
totally yeah very very good question
and you're right to see a motion uh
kind of touching on all three which is
to say when you view emotion from
development where you could view emotion
from installment or you could view
emotion from
transcendent if you want to kind of hold
them as frames
and so yeah in the in the transcendent
you're looking at phase
shifts in emotion that have to do with
the exercise of
will in the control of emotion now
that's the most one of the most basic
elements
and that's aided through symbol and as i
said the
depersonalization trans personalization
those kinds of things
and so that's kind of like kind of get
that insolence actually much more
complicated because in solomon you're
you're trying to actually kind of let go
of the will
to go down and into emotion uh
and so like as i was saying when you're
crying and your imagination is
spontaneously producing
images of the thing that you're crying
about
that's tremendously informative
information
just as a dream is but a dream is also
not willed
you're not willing the dream and dreams
can be tremendously emotional
so the notion of insolent is actually
like to find a way to kind of quote
unquote explore
emotions to go into the underworld of
emotion
um which is easier to do if you have
strong transcendent
practice right so and so those kind of
interanimate but the more i can explore
emotion through insolent the more
i can learn to work with emotion in the
domain of the
transcendent so this is one of the
notions of tantra
basically right that actually you don't
want to stop
anger from arising you actually
sometimes want to make anger arise
precisely so they
have the opportunity to work with it
uh and so that's that dynamic and then
in development
that's where you get a whole bunch of
kind of cognitive behavioral therapy
script rewriting there's a whole bunch
of things you can do
that actually turn emotion and reveal
its linguistic and cognitive dimensions
so that's worth
and so that's like one branch of it and
the other branch is that
you actually need cognition and often a
whole bunch of
kind of reflective and cultural kind of
assets
to understand the image and the emotion
that comes with image
so like the craziest things that happen
is when people have dreams
and the dreams like and of course this
is classic jung
the dream's just it's a myth
like it's literally a myth from some
ancient culture
and they have never heard this never
read it or anything like that
and they go to a psychologist or a
friend or whatever or they even google
the image that came to them
and they get this whole thing and then
they start in the
they went from okay you spontaneously
given an image
in the process of installment and it
forces you in the domain of development
to build a whole bunch of knowledge
about the world
and a whole bunch of like reframing of
like history
and causality like how did you even have
that dream and like a whole bunch of
other stuff
so that that's the kind of place where
in the domain of development sometimes
you need
to be equipped there to be able to
basically
work with image and
like i said one of the basic processes
of extracting the symbol from the image
to go transcendent and change phase of
emotion
that's it
you can't identify the symbol in the
dream unless you're a jungian
psychologist and you've read
30 books on like you know mythic
archetypes um so there's that
dimensionality where cognition
aids in transcendence as well by being
able to identify universal
uh pattern so
so yeah awesome question thank you
can you hear me now yes
all right yeah i
i i just i guess i'm getting
a bunch of beeps and stuff so um but
what i was going to say is that the
symbolic
was was for purse thirdness
and and to him it signified something
like
libraries like accumulated knowledge and
and understanding um and
secondness was indices um
which would be contrast it would be uh
how do you come up with a measurement
system
to decide what you're going to theorize
about
and so forth firstness would be sort of
what you want to get back to which is
everything is coal and
and you know there are no there are no
particular problems and stuff like that
and you're just
being and maybe you're being in ecstasy
or something like that and it's in the
in the contrast just suddenly the
ecstasy stops and you
and you want to do something about that
you want to get back to the ecstasy or
something
and uh the second the second question i
had
um had to do with uh how does
um how does mcluhan's tetrad
uh fit into this the the notion of the
enhancement i'm sure figures into it in
terms of development
uh a technological enhancement that
in turn changes the mentality
uh acts on the brain rewires the brain
it obsolesces something that had gone
before so
a bunch of behaviors and habits that we
have become used to
are no longer relevant and they go into
the past
we retrieve something from the past uh
we retrieve a bunch of habits and stuff
like that because of the new technology
but it relates to something that we've
experienced before
have forgotten and then
finally the notion of reversal which is
the way i see it is when something is
pushed past its limit
when you haven't defined limits for it
like let's say you haven't really
defined limits for anti-racism
when you've achieved it so at a certain
point
you push it past its limit and
anti-racism becomes racism
so it does the opposite of what you
originally intended for it to do
fascinating yeah i hadn't thought about
it
uh so that's an interesting
characterization of purses triple
uh and you could see just from listening
to that how it might slot in to the
three that i'm
speaking to mcloone's is is deeper and a
little bit more interesting because it's
both
how does that phenomenon affect the
three
which is to say how is insolent
different now in the digital
as opposed to the electric as opposed to
the
uh gutenberg galaxy as opposed to the
oral right
so that's fascinating if the three have
always existed
as the basic dimensions of psyche how
have we been reconfigured
in our cyclical unfolding in these
different
kind of environments of technology and
media so that's like a whole
huge door to open and think about
and then his more detailed work on
enhancement retrieval
and what was the other one enhancement
retrieval
uh enhancement um
obsolescence retrieval and reversal
reversal you're in return yeah that's
really interesting i have to think more
about that
that would allow us to answer a little
bit about
that prior question about what's so
different now
during the digital and
both across development and solomon and
transcendence so that's
pretty heavy cool thank you scott i'll
put it on my docket
to interanimate with mcluhan a little
bit more
and john you had a question
hey zach hey
um my dad's a psychiatrist and so this
feels like a very important moment for
me to have so many of these
things that i learned at the dinner
table come to me at such a
such a level of principle and
abstraction and
understanding so thank you um
my question is i've been similarly
stunned by greg henrique's work
that i've come across this year and
trying to figure out how to mesh that
with what you're saying um i'd be very
curious to hear you talk about that
i was just speaking to greg hendricks
about that question uh
on monday or friday i can't remember uh
i mean basically they're
they're both uh metapsychologists
so like um they're both operating in
that domain between the special sciences
and fields of psychology
and what's often called metaphysics or
philosophy
so in that sense they're in the same
family of
work and i see them
more or less as complement
detailed work to do where i could take
part of
henrik's model and show how my triple
arises within the architecture of his
frame
um so i think that's work that could be
done which i'm not going to do here
so far i haven't seen any places where
like my model suggests that
there's inadequacies or absences i think
it actually might be the reverse
um i think the main difference is
probably aesthetic
which is to say i think greg is much
more attempting to address
scientists in the fields of psychology
to get them to attempt to basically
change the way they understand their own
scientific practice
whereas i'm not attempting to do that
basically at all
i'm attempting to speak to people like
you all
who are interested in the field of
psychology especially to try to help
themselves and others
navigate an increasingly crisis-ridden
and
kind of frightening and uh fascinating
world
um so i'm much more in that dimension
trying to
kind of like go and end around from the
academy and go directly kind of
to the people so in that sense maybe
it's a little bit more wilburian that
i'm just trying to say okay
psychology like and so greg has his work
cut out for him i think because it's
very difficult to move
in the established fields of psychology
and to try to get them to
change their practices which many of
which by virtue of greg's modeling look
absurd
like category errors and definitional
inadequacies
and methodological uh like
fiction basically so in that respect
i love greg's work but i do think mine
might be a little bit less
ambitious in that respect and a little
bit more aesthetically focused
to be directly
useful to non-specialists in psychology
or something something like that
but i'm continuing to try to think about
the detail work
and figure out how i can kind of like
incorporate more of greg's modeling
into the aesthetics of my kind of like
framing
um that would probably be one way to
think about it but i'm very happy that
yeah his is getting the attention it
deserves
you know wilbur's integral psychology i
think is another one of that
kind of scope and there's a couple other
pretty interesting ones elliot jacks is
um uh you know the one laid out
in revisioning psychology uh by james
hillman i thought about the beginning of
this putting up a list of books of like
comparable metapsychological projects
but
i didn't so so that's a little bit to
that
my sense is that at some point maybe
greg and i'll write
together or do a call where we both
speak and do some of that detailed work
and then also show that
irrespective of how the detail work
hashes out there's an alignment
of focus and
a lot of what we're saying is is very
identical in fact
so cool thank you
if you don't mind me asking a quick
follow-up um as a layman with both of
these in my head
do you have a helpful way of kind of
slotting them together like accesses or
ways because i i'm
i'm struggling sometimes with both of
the thoughts in the last two weeks
coming to mind
well the first thing i'll say is like to
have that struggle
is an awesome struggle to have like
that's the the kabbalah say something
like you know difficulties in the realms
of delight
you know so it's like when you're
working at meta
levels with those types of models you
have to understand that like the task
demand of that cognitively it's like
it's huge so that you're confused makes
me think you're doing a good job
this is the advice i tend to
thank you if you figured it all out
you probably didn't if you're confused
it means you're actually in the learning
process
uh so that's my first bit of advice
which is like don't try to be really
quickly
that these are actually really big rich
models and trying to inner animate them
could be complex and difficult my
general
sense would be a couple fold one is that
you know you can slot a lot of the stuff
into greg's model there's it's actually
full of triples
already so you could identify that
that's one basic move
is to just take greg's model as primary
and to go hunting through it for
transcendence and soulmate development
basically
use mine as a category scheme to try to
like
slightly re-categorize him so that's one
way to go
um you know i think you can use the work
i'm doing in development
to actually shore up some of greg's
models uh where he doesn't bring in
piaget and other folks like that
so there's a good actual additional kind
of amendment or appendix to greg's model
which would be something like that
talk i just gave on development which
doesn't contradict anything of what he
said but actually
unpacks a lot of how development
actually formally takes place
and yeah so that's a that's a little bit
but the main thing i would say is yeah
just keep
reading greg's work uh unfortunately i
haven't written anything
as in depth uh so but i yeah i'd be
curious
um yeah reaching you know getting greg
and i together to speak i think might be
a good idea
although we may just confuse you more so
but we'll see
thank you um arie had a question
go ahead and ask it hey brother
hey zach how you doing buddy all right
so
i you know the chapter five of your book
talks about this gaffney's unique self
theory
and i think that my question is more
like
how it how that chapter and this
conversation
relates to my own confusion as
to what spiritual development looks like
through the buddhist thing you know it's
like
i i felt very validated by reading that
because i
like the idea of dissolving into nobody
doesn't really
entice me that much for whatever reason
and so
i was hoping you could like i don't know
help me kind of
understand the post-modern conception of
spiritual development
and what those two lenses might
lend totally yeah uh
thank you for that question um
so a few things on that one is
uh this aside by
james hillman in the book uh
poohair and cenex and it's about the
difference between
soul and spirit
which is very important which is
actually a difference that exists in a
whole bunch of traditions
but which was written out of the kind of
catholic church
and they outlawed images as well
so it's worth noting that the idea of
something like
life mind or spirit
something like that as a kind of great
chain of being
if you want to go there and the
difference between
insolent and transcendence being the
work at the level of soul and work at
the level of spirit
and so in that essay by hillman which is
like beautiful i think it's called
peaks and veils or something like that
which is peaks and valleys
in the essay by hillman he
gives this excerpt from a letter from
the dalai lama
where the dalai lama is trying to
basically explain the differences
between these different
forms of practice basically between soul
work
which actually exists in some forms of
buddhism and spirit work
which also exists in some forms of
buddhism
and so he said like you know once there
were these beautiful
it tells a story an image actually
paints an image which is interesting
once there were these beautiful monks
and they went to this valley
and they set up a monastery and the
valley was
lush with greenery and there were
streams going through it they had
mud in it and there was light and there
was dark and they chanted
and it was awesome and then a few monks
even more beautiful went up
into the mountains out of the valley the
plants disappeared
the glaciers were there kind of like
just geometric
perfection a single flower bloomed with
like ornate
beauty and they set up a monastery and
they did no
chanting right and it was even better
so that's his way of like painting an
image
of the difference between soul and
spirit work
right where the soul work is the work in
the valley
with all these different shades of green
and light and darkness and the muds and
the valley
and all of those things and spirit work
is that work that takes place
high up in the kind of geometric
perfection
of the glaciers um kind of where there's
only light
uh and sounds travel very far and this
single flower
blooms uh and so generally speaking
like a practice like zen buddhism for
example
or vipassana meditation
um or many of what wilbur would call the
ascending
paths even certain forms of
contemplative prayer and
jungian symbol work that this stuff
takes place up
on the peaks where uh
basically uh totally
amazing beautiful forms of transpersonal
experience can take place
but that's not the full
dimensionality of psychic growth that's
possible
and so there's the dimension of work
that's in solomon based
which is also trans personal work which
is also to say it's technically speaking
spiritual
it's not it's in the realm of soul and
there's spiritual work that's in the
realm
working normal soul is not less personal
um it's just uh again
not an up and out into an impersonality
but a down and in into a uniqueness
right and so gaffney's model originally
articulated book called soul prince
um is that notion that yes the
transcendence huge
but you don't go up to the peak and then
stay up at the peak you go up to the
peak and then you actually come back
down
that's not mountain climbing works you
can't live on the peak by definition
uh it's quite inhospitable uh
um but gorgeous views you have to get
down
back in to the valley so the notion of
unique self is that you need to
disappear into
oneness and experience the lack of
cognition lack of object awareness
lack of self-identity story just bodily
attention
and consciousness as such like important
experience
even for emotional self-regulation and
knowing what
the nature of self is like
but that is actually reintegrated
into whatever process of installment you
are at
going down and into your life and so
the risk of joining the beautiful monks
up on the peaks
uh is that you can get stuck
up there um and so you see people with
these kind of dual life
kind of trajectories where the sense of
having to flee the world
to go live on the peak is the only way
to be spiritual
um uh and so that notion of bringing the
soul and spirit practices
together was what hillman was trying to
recommend
and uh so in a concrete way
if you're working with your tension and
your consciousness and symbol as
part of your practice then you're doing
spirit work transcendence which is great
if you're working with image imagination
personality uh and archetypal
imagery in particular then you're doing
insolent work
uh and if you're building the cognitive
apparatus which by the way is sometimes
a lot more important
given how complex the world is like i'm
always like maybe read some long ass
books
instead of meditating all day that's
another conversation
you also need to work in that domain of
development
or else all of that stuff as deep as
your consciousness has become
uh you're equipped you know
to do very little because you don't have
the languages and the cognitive capacity
and the fidelity with objects in the
world and stuff
so all three need to be going uh
and so yeah if you're doing that
language cognition capacity so just
think like how much of my practices are
in the domain of working with my own
awareness
to use the will to regulate my emotion
and how much of my practices are in the
domain of activating
constructive imagination working with
images
moving through stations deepening
personality like they're
just they're related but they're
distinct
yes you see that in buddhism and then
the higher yoga
tantras like
things like that where they engage with
imaginal exercises
and archetypal imagery very directly
but you find it in most traditions in
some way or another
all right so one more question thank you
all right double question about it
thanks
okay i so one more question zach one
more question i'll do it to try to do it
quick
all right uh so chris chris eddie had a
question
chris what's up how's it going
yeah i wanted to ask it could be
formulated in a few ways but the way i
wrote it was what are the open questions
you have about the formulation of the
metapsychology
both from a theoretical and a practical
standpoint
um so what do you feel you need to
clarify about it
you know what kind of images do you have
for it like what do you
wish it would become things like that
thank you chris um
yeah it's interesting i think mostly
what i'm feeling a need for as i speak
it with you all
is to write about it um because it is uh
slippery feels slippery like as i speak
about it like i think i'm giving
clarity and i think it's coming across
but i also think that
um there's a difference between speech
and text
so i think putting it into some written
form
will be quite powerful um
you know most of my open questions have
to do with
well there's two sets there's the detail
work which is like i describe like
okay does this actually work like okay
let's take this psychological model
see if i can oh i make sense of it great
i can basically run it through some
iterations
of application across fields of
psychology
and questions in psychology which is
what we're going to start doing next
week with the practicum
like if we can't solve basic
problems staring us in our face that
have to do with our own psyche
with the metapsychology then it's not
worth anything so
it needs to be tested we need to kick
the tires and
and really see if it's going to work as
an applied
psychology um and then i'd also like to
see
uh yeah basically
you know i think for me it's about what
actually could work
in our culture to get
the mental health crisis uh
resolved or at least
um stop it from continuing to get worse
um and so that's much broader question
than my i'm out of psychology i actually
have no pretense of thinking i
that this work will do that but when i
think about like what's the vision
in that is that we need to figure out
some way like
um to stop this cascading
pattern of
um which the psyche is kind of like
embroiled in
and so it's like but how do we do that
well it's with the psyche oh that sucks
so it's like they're so it's like we
have to find a way to again
get the psyche to like throw water on
its own face
or to like look in the mirror somehow so
what what does that actually look like
at a cultural level
um aside from like war uh
i don't know and so most of what i'm
doing is
an attempt to just like fumble in those
directions
uh which um
which hopefully you know the next
generation will pick
up or this generation will pick up and
experiment with
um so that that's a little bit of how i
of how i see it at this point it's super
nascent
there needs to be writing done there
needs to be application
thinking about all the things and then
there needs to be thinking about you
know
the broader field of effect that one
would want to get going
so cool thank you chris
um so that's all she wrote
same time next week uh we'll wrap the
transcendent slides and then my
invitation would be
to not bring questions about the model
you can but bring questions about the
world
that the model could be used to address
and then we'll learn more about the
model as we try to address it
and the world includes your own neuroses
and minds
uh and pathologies and the world also
includes culture
um media landscapes uh
entertainment artifacts all kinds of
stuff so i'm totally open to
fielding and having conversations about
some interesting stuff next week
um and seeing how the model
kind of works so it's a lot of fun guys
i really appreciate this opportunity
so great to see you thank you so much
zach
i'm gonna tag peter in
cool thank you nicholas thank you zach
um
just gonna plug uh a few events uh one
coming up
at 6 30 p.m eastern time which i'll put
in the chat right now
so we're having a series called
postscript where there's a platform
called letter.wiki they have exchanges
people have debates on in the letter
format
and so we're teaming up with them and
having uh like post post-letter
exchanges at the stoa and there's one on
toxic masculinity with buster benson
author of uh why re-arguing and then
john davis
uh he has his blog a youtube channel
called war elephant and he's a former
marine
and they're basically going to argue the
question is
um is the term toxic masculinity more
helpful
or more harmful um so that is going to
be tonight at 6 30 pm it should be
feisty and then uh with richard
richard bartlett and ronan harrington
they're coming in tomorrow at 10 a.m
eastern time and they're having a
workshop on depolarizing conversations
so that should be pretty cool so i'll uh
take nick back in
great thank you everybody hope to see
you next week for the third session
uh how does one how does one get on the
discord
server yeah i will uh um put that in the
chat right now
okay cool
right thanks again everybody we'll see
you next week for another session